<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-17T11:04:53+00:00</updated><id>https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple logbook of Linh </subtitle><entry><title type="html">I use Arch, btw</title><link href="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2025/arch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I use Arch, btw"/><published>2025-03-04T19:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-04T19:45:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2025/arch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2025/arch/"><![CDATA[<p>At 2am, you know, holy hour of random ideas. I feel frustrated that I am using <strong>Pop!_OS 22.04</strong>. It’s already 2025, we should have 24.04 version. Took me a while to do the research, and I heard that the dev team is migrating Pop!_OS to COSMOS. A uncerntain feeling captured my mind.</p> <blockquote> <p>“What if they just drop out half way?”</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="what-are-my-options">What are my options?</h2> <p>My mind wants to change to a new OS. What about Ubuntu? But it’s too basic and Gnome has too much flaws, the idea of installing extensions and stuffs make me exhausted.</p> <p>Fedora? Kali Linux? Debian? Too many distros to choose, life is too short.</p> <p>I want a fun and challenging OS to play with. And yes, I choose <strong>Arch</strong>.</p> <p>Finally becoming an Arch user seems cool tbh.</p> <h2 id="embrace-the-adventure">Embrace the adventure</h2> <p>It wasn’t easy to install arch. I tried to follow the tutorial from chatGPT but it sucks when come to partitioning part.</p> <p>I had to install arch twice to be able to boot in. The dual boot story made me stuck for a while.</p> <p>When I remove the media, boot into arch. <strong>Boom</strong>. It’s a black screen, no GUI no internet. Yup, I didn’t believe that I have to install internet service manually.</p> <p>Then I had to insert the USB third time to install internet and GUI. I choose KDE as it seems better than GNOME. (Or maybe the grass is greener on the other side).</p> <h2 id="my-arch-setup">My Arch Setup</h2> <p>I use <strong>Sweet Theme and Candy icons</strong> of this chad <a href="https://github.com/EliverLara">EliverLara</a></p> <p>My main coding editor: <strong>nvim with AstroNvim+Konsole</strong>. I don’t reuse my nvim setup at Pop!_OS. I tried to switch to Nvchad but I am not familiar with its workflow. Kitty terminal’s NerdFont problem made me feel tired.</p> <p>Terminal emulator: <strong>Alacritty</strong>. I love its opacity :wink:</p> <p>My note-taking and research setup: <strong>Zotero+Obsidian</strong>. I tried to use Mendeley but it’s too slow to me. And maybe I will write a tutorial another day to show my workflow of Zotero+Obsidian.</p> <p>Mail Client: <strong>Thunderbird</strong>. Can’t find better solution.</p> <p>Browser: <strong>Firefox</strong>. But with the drama recently about its privacy. I am considering other options.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Linh-the-Engineer"/><category term="cse"/><category term="english"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a brief story of my try on archlinux]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Đại đội trưởng của tôi - của anh, của chúng ta</title><link href="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/dai-doi-truong-cua-toi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Đại đội trưởng của tôi - của anh, của chúng ta"/><published>2024-11-03T09:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-03T09:15:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/dai-doi-truong-cua-toi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/dai-doi-truong-cua-toi/"><![CDATA[<p>Đây là vở chèo được khách VIP nhà ta vô cùng tâm đắc giới thiệu nên mình không thể không xem. Và người ấy quả thực đã không khiến mình thất vọng, một vở chèo sâu sắc về mặt nội dung và ấn tượng về mặt dàn dựng sân khấu.</p> <p>Đầu tiên phải nói đây không phải là kịch bản gốc mà được chuyển thể từ vở kịch cùng tên, mình sẽ không xem nốt vở kịch rồi đâm bang so sánh.</p> <p>Về kịch bản, tác phẩm làm về đề tài chiến tranh nhưng không cụ thể một trận chiến nào cả. Nó giống như một lát cắt rất nhỏ trong hơn 20 năm trời Kháng chiến chống Mỹ. Mà vì vậy, ta thấy được sâu sắc hơn về nội tâm của các chiến sĩ. Bởi cuộc chiến lớn nào cũng vậy, họ dễ bị coi là con số hơn là con người.</p> <p>Cách dàn dựng có hai nhân vật trung tâm với một con người có tài năng nhưng tư tưởng vẫn có phần khiếm khuyết cùng một con người tuy có thể không giỏi bằng nhưng thẳng thắn, chân tình khiến mình không khỏi nhớ tới tác phẩm Chiến tranh và Hòa bình của Lev Tolstoy.</p> <p>Vở chèo là diễn biến, phát triển nội tâm của nhiều nhân vật, từ anh đại đội trưởng tới sư đoàn trưởng, từ người con tới người cha. Vở chèo còn là cách xử lí các mối quan hệ giữa người với người trong thời điểm đạn bom ác liệt, giữa anh yêu em yêu, giữa cấp trên cấp dưới, giữa cha con, và giữa đồng đội với nhau. Để rồi bằng tình cảm yêu thương, thái độ thẳng thắn chân thành mà các nhân vật của chúng ta trưởng thành hơn, cùng cống hiến cho thắng lợi chung.</p> <p>Về dàn dựng sân khấu, mình ấn tượng nhất ở 3 phân đoạn. Đầu tiên là 2 nam chính đang cãi nhau hăng máu thì hồi tưởng rồi sang sông luôn, ôi thề là nó mượt như sunsilk. Thứ hai là đoạn miêu tả nội tâm của đứa con nhớ mẹ, bởi vì loại hình sân khấu thường nặng về kể, làm những đoạn độc thoại cho hay không phải dễ và họ làm hay tới mức mình bất ngờ. Thứ ba là phân cảnh 16+ nhỏ của đôi chim cu dưới hầm, dựng rất khéo, khán giả xem biết người ta đang chim chuột nhưng không bị thô thiển. Đánh đèn cũng rất có ý tứ, nhiều cảnh thành bại là nhờ ánh sáng luôn. Cách điều khiển nhịp độ cân bằng giữa bi và hài, giữa lúc căng thẳng và bông lơi cũng là một điểm đáng khen ngợi, không khiến người xem thấy nhàm chán hay căng thẳng quá độ.</p> <p>Tựu chung, Đại đội trưởng của tôi có hàm lượng nghệ thuật đủ cao, có nội dung đủ chiều sâu và phức tạp để ngẫm nghĩ. Một tác phẩm đáng xem.</p> <p>Cảm ơn vì đại ca đã giới thiệu thêm một tác phẩm đáng nhớ về mặt nội dung lẫn nghệ thuật chứ không phải vì ức chế nên đáng nhớ. Đúng là đại ca của bọn em có khác, trộm vía, trộm vía.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Stories-of-Culture"/><category term="chèo"/><category term="vietnamese"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cảm nhận về vở chèo Đại đội trưởng của tôi]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Khăn Piêu rơi ở chốn nào - Để người khách cũ lao xao trong lòng</title><link href="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/chiec-khan-pieu-ca-lon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Khăn Piêu rơi ở chốn nào - Để người khách cũ lao xao trong lòng"/><published>2024-09-10T14:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-10T14:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/chiec-khan-pieu-ca-lon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/chiec-khan-pieu-ca-lon/"><![CDATA[<p>Đại văn hào Victor Hugo từng có một câu nói mà mình tạm dịch là:<br/> “<em>Lịch sử là gì? Là tiếng vọng của quá khứ tới tương lai; là phản chiếu của tương lai về quá khứ</em>”.</p> <p>Ngược dòng thời gian, quay về với “Chín năm làm một Điện Biên/ Nên cành hoa đỏ nên thiên sử vàng”, ta có nhạc sĩ Doãn Nho thời trai trẻ phụng sự cho Cách mạng, cho Độc lập, Tự do của Dân tộc. Khi ấy, tình yêu quê hương đất nước, tình yêu đồng bào đã vượt lên trên tất cả thứ tình cảm khác.</p> <p>Mà nhắc tới đây, ai lại không nhớ tới bài thơ <em>Việt Bắc</em> của Tố Hữu:</p> <blockquote> <p>”- Mình về mình có nhớ ta?<br/> Mười lăm năm ấy thiết tha mặn nồng.<br/> Mình về mình có nhớ không<br/> Nhìn cây nhớ núi, nhìn sông nhớ nguồn?…”</p> </blockquote> <p>Đến 1–2 năm sau chiến thắng, nhạc sĩ mới quay lại chốn xưa, lòng lại rộn chút “tình riêng” từ bài dân ca dân tộc Xá <em>Tăng A Tim</em> để viết bài hát “Chiếc khăn rơi”, sau đổi tên thành “Chiếc khăn Piêu”. Khăn Piêu là chiếc khăn của cô gái dân tộc Thái dùng để làm tín vật cho tình yêu của mình.</p> <p>Bài hát được phát triển từ dân ca dân tộc Xá, hình tượng chính là chiếc khăn của dân tộc Thái, phải chăng đây chính là một câu trả lời cho câu “Mình về mình có nhớ ta?” của người miền xuôi cho người miền ngược?</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Quay về hiện tại tới với tiết mục của Nhà Cá Lớn.</strong></p> <blockquote> <p>“Khăn Piêu dệt gió vươn cành,</p> <p>Trái tim người lính quân hành xốn xang.</p> <p>Bước chân mấy ải quan san,</p> <p>Sau lưng điểm tựa bản làng quê hương!”</p> </blockquote> <p>4 câu thể lục bát, thể thơ truyền thống dân tộc ta mở đầu cho tiết mục Nhà Cá Lớn.</p> <p>Nghe chú Tự Long ngâm, lòng lại nghĩ tới mấy câu trong <em>Chinh Phụ Ngâm</em> của Đặng Trần Côn:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Trang phong lưu đang chừng niên thiếu,</p> <p>Sánh nhau cùng dan díu chữ duyên.</p> <p>Nỡ nào đôi lứa thiếu niên,</p> <p>Quan san để cách hàn huyên cho đành!”</p> </blockquote> <p><em>Chinh Phụ Ngâm</em> là khúc ai oán của người thiếu phụ có chồng ra trận, mang đậm nỗi lo cho tình yêu lứa đôi của mình. Với Nhà Cá Lớn, tình yêu đôi lứa không dừng lại ở chút tình riêng nam nữ, mà được phát triển lên thành tình yêu quê hương đất nước.</p> <hr/> <p>Trong tác phẩm <em>Hoàng tử bé</em> của Antoine de Saint-Exupéry có một câu như thế này:<br/> “<em>…Khi ông nhìn trời, bởi vì ở một trong những ngôi sao đó có tôi, bởi vì trong một ngôi sao đó có tôi cười, nên ông sẽ tưởng chừng tất cả các ngôi sao đều cười…</em>”</p> <p>Phải chăng ở đây Nhà Cá Lớn cũng nghĩ như vậy — khi nghĩ về bản làng, bởi vì ở một trong những bản làng đó có người con gái trao anh chiếc khăn Piêu, nên tất cả bản làng trở thành điểm tựa, lí do để anh chiến đấu.</p> <hr/> <p><strong>Và đoạn X-part của Soobin được viết như sau:</strong></p> <blockquote> <p>“Tôi bước trên con đường gai đầy</p> <p>Mang theo cả Tổ quốc trên vai vẫn còn đong đầy</p> <p>Thân nam mười tấc anh chẳng quản nắng trưa</p> <p>Băng ngàn dặm đồi trùng mịt mùng chẳng ngại gió mưa</p> <p>Khăn Piêu chờ ai, nơi đây cỏ hương đâm chồi rót mật vào tai</p> <p>Chờ một ngày hai ta chung đôi dù cho hai nơi xa xôi”</p> </blockquote> <p>Ngoài tính biểu trưng rất cao về những người lính biên phòng, về khát vọng tình yêu lứa đôi, mình còn không khỏi liên tưởng tới hình ảnh về một bậc cái thế anh hùng — cụ thể là Từ Hải trong <em>Truyện Kiều</em> của đại thi hào Nguyễn Du:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Râu hùm, hàm én, mày ngài</p> <p>Vai năm tấc rộng, thân mười thước cao.”</p> </blockquote> <p>Mình rất yêu thích cách những bài hát có bề dày lịch sử được viết thêm phần X-part vẫn hòa hợp với bài gốc bởi sự tinh tế và chiều sâu trong từng chữ được thêm vào.</p> <hr/> <p>Ngày xưa nhạc sĩ Doãn Nho, chàng lính trẻ gắn bó với Việt Bắc nảy nở rung động chút tình riêng từ cái tình chung viết ra bài hát này. Mấy mươi năm sau, Nhà Cá Lớn thể hiện lại dựa vào cái tình riêng đó dẫn đến tình chung, còn được viết dành tặng cho những người lính biên phòng.</p> <p><strong>Có phải đây chính là cách quá khứ vọng tới tương lai, tương lai phản chiếu về quá khứ?</strong></p> <p><strong>Có phải đây chính là lí do nhạc sĩ Doãn Nho “rất xúc động” khi được nghe tác phẩm này?</strong></p> <p><strong>Có phải đây chính là cách một tác phẩm vượt qua thử thách của thời gian và cách người nghệ sĩ thực thụ làm nghề?</strong></p> <hr/> <p>Còn ti tỉ thứ để khen về các anh Nhà Cá Lớn trong bài hát này nhưng mình xin phép dừng lại ở đây.</p> <p>Rất xúc động khi nghe bài hát, rất tự hào về chú Tự Long khi được nghe chú chia sẻ về quá trình làm bài hát này.</p> <p><strong>P/S</strong>: Người viết không có chuyên môn về văn hóa - nghệ thuật nên không tránh khỏi sai sót, rất mở lòng đón nhận góp ý.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Stories-of-Culture"/><category term="music"/><category term="vietnamese"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cảm nhận về tiết mục Chiếc Khăn Piêu của nhà Cá Lớn trong chương trình ATVNCG 2024]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quantum first reflection</title><link href="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/quantum-first-reflection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantum first reflection"/><published>2024-06-09T22:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T22:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/quantum-first-reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/quantum-first-reflection/"><![CDATA[<p>Dear readers,</p> <p>It’s my honor to share you about this. Last night, I received the email took me days waiting in worries. I passed the interview and successfully join the High Performance Quantum Computing Team at my university.</p> <p><em>Now I have to rewrite my LinkedIn profile, About section of this blog and fulfill the oath I took.</em></p> <p>What will I do in this post? Maybe sharing a little detail about my true thoughts on this intersection. I hope that through this, I can sort my memories and ideas in a structural way.</p> <h2 id="what-do-i-truly-want-to-do">What do I truly want to do?</h2> <p>I have decided to pursue IT since grade 8th? Or even earlier, but I announced that to my parents in grade 8.</p> <p>When I do the interview for my internship, I will say that I love it since a CNET article about smart house. Yes, that’s the factor I want to do IoT, Embedded Systems instead of web development but not the answer for “why do you choose IT?”. The another factor that I love C/C++ and I hate JS with a passion.</p> <p>The real start for my obsession with this engineering is a long story involving a lot of old friends and foes. So I prefer not telling it. And honestly, I forgot the story.</p> <p>But I am really grateful of this decision. I love the feeling when I code, when I have bugs, when I spend hours just to make my terminal a little bit more shiny.</p> <p>So why do you apply into HPQC Lab? Did you lie about your motives to get into the lab?</p> <p>I apply it, because I once thought about quantum computers. And in my faraway dream, I wanted to become a researcher.</p> <blockquote> <p>“Bachelor 4 years. Master 2 years. PhD 3 years. Then die.” - Once Linh’s plan of life.</p> </blockquote> <p>When I entered university, that dream became hopeless. So I feel really excited when I see the announcement. It’s my last chance.</p> <p>As my <em>bot</em> Lord Elrond once said:</p> <blockquote> <p>“Greatness is often achieved not because one feels entirely ready, but because one is willing to rise to the occasion despite uncertainties. Even if the road seems steep, your willingness to ascend is a testament to your readiness for the journey.”</p> </blockquote> <p>I am proud that I won’t make myself regret. I truly have a genuine interest for quantum computing, because it is hard, it is exciting and it can shake the foundation of Computer Science. Doing elegant things like that makes me feel alive.</p> <p>And I vow that I will pursue this path until the end of the world if I pass into the lab. So, waiting for my weird posts about Quantum Computing and more “nerdy” stuffs.</p> <h2 id="what-will-you-do">What will you do?</h2> <p>I have to follow the onboarding process of the lab while doing my internship. Beside that, I have to save money for my Master. I also need to improve my GPA. So that means I have no time to waste. I have to allocate my time for my hobbies, my entertainment and my studies in a suitable way. I have to come to the war prepared.</p> <p>German is also a higher priority now. Because you know, you are pretty sure that you will go to Germany someday if you pursue this path. Don’t be afraid to get rid of some other languages with poetic purposes. You can start it later if one day your German level is similar to your English one.</p> <p>That leads to I need to stop staying up late permanently. The plan in detail I won’t share here, but this post will prepare mentally for myself.</p> <hr/> <p>Thank you so much for staying with me. Thank you for not giving up, my dear Linh.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Journal-of-Sciences"/><category term="cse"/><category term="english"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a brief story of my try on archlinux]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">my neovim kickstart - new tool that I love</title><link href="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/nvim-kickstart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="my neovim kickstart - new tool that I love"/><published>2024-06-07T18:08:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-07T18:08:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/nvim-kickstart</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/nvim-kickstart/"><![CDATA[<p>Hello my dears,</p> <p>It’s fun to announce that I am officially moving from VSC to nvim. It isn’t a smooth, comfortable experience. So I am here to share my journey and hope you can find it’s inspiring to try nvim yourself!</p> <h2 id="story">story</h2> <p>I had a dream to play with vim some years ago. But it’s really struggling to do. I heard about the power of vim, but when I try it, I ask myself: How they can make a terminal text editor that “powerful”? I can’t see any advantages from vim and the commands are confusing like hell. And that time, I also had a big love for VSC. So “using vim is elegant and chad” idea stuck in my mind, but I don’t want to mess with it.</p> <p>Further on my university journey, I had to use terminal editor sometimes. I also avoided vim at all cost and used Nano instead. But then during my internship, something happen!</p> <p>My mentor is better than me, of course. I don’t mention about coding skills and knowledge, but even his skill when using VSC is far better than me. And then he recommended me to use the keyboard more. So when he had to go to an exhibition and I am alone in the office, I spent my whole day dedicating for nvim, to become a chad dev so my mentor won’t make fun of me anymore!</p> <p>I did it, with a lot of pain and mistakes. So now I am here to give you some advice based on my experience.</p> <h2 id="kickstart">kickstart</h2> <p>First, I use Ubuntu. So that means this article is heavily based on this distro, I think it’s similar to other platforms but idk.</p> <p>I don’t use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sudo apt install nvim</code> to install nvim. Instead of, I use PPA repo in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">unstable</code>. Why? Cause when I try to install plugins for nvim, I realize that my nvim version is too old. Maybe Ubuntu 23.04 and 24.04 have better updates but whatever.</p> <p>So after installing, you will find that nvim has nothing! Except some cool commands! Before digging deeper to custom vim, I highly recommend you to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">:Tutor</code> to start with the power of vim.</p> <p>Now you have some options to do. You can explore <a href="https://www.lazyvim.org/">LazyVim</a> or <a href="https://nvchad.com/">Nvchad</a> for easy experience. I am currently using <a href="https://github.com/nvim-lua/kickstart.nvim">kickstart</a>. But I am really considering moving to Nvchad. Haha. <em>Tried to move to Nvchad while writing this post but it’s not a good experience comparing to kickstart</em>.</p> <p>So I use <a href="https://sw.kovidgoyal.net/kitty/">kitty terminal</a> as the home for nvim. Cause when you click on the nvim icon, it will open the terminal instead, lol. Because my terminal is zsh so here is the code to automatically open nvim when click kitty.</p> <div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># Check if the terminal is Kitty and launch Neovim</span>
<span class="k">if</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$TERM</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">"xterm-kitty"</span> <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then
    </span><span class="nb">exec </span>nvim
<span class="k">fi</span>

</code></pre></div></div> <p>Also remember to install <a href="https://www.nerdfonts.com/font-downloads">nerdfonts</a>, I personally only download the Icon Only package.</p> <h2 id="customize-kickstart">customize kickstart</h2> <p>After following the guide to install kickstart. You will open its config file by typing: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">:e $MYVIMRC</code>.</p> <p>You can follow the file to custom your vim. I installed some other plugins like dashboard, git-flog, some shortcuts and stuffs. If you want to take a peek, visit at my github repo: <a href="https://github.com/vtrnnhlinh/kickstart.nvim">vtrnnhlinh/kickstart.nvim</a>.</p> <hr/> <p>If you have any questions, feel free to comment or send me an email. Danke Viele! I feel like this is a bad tutorial whatsoever…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Linh-the-Engineer"/><category term="cse"/><category term="english"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a brief story of my try on archlinux]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My IELTS Journey</title><link href="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/ielts-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My IELTS Journey"/><published>2024-01-12T23:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-12T23:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/ielts-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://vtrnnhlinh.github.io/blog/2024/ielts-review/"><![CDATA[<p>Finally, I got my IELTS certificate. Even though I got a normal result (6.5), but I guess this is a fun journey to share.</p> <h2 id="preparation">Preparation</h2> <p>First step for every exam is preparation, but I didn’t register to learn at any English center. I feel like it’s actually a <em>scam</em>. So I got my self-study plan.</p> <h3 id="prepare-for-the-exam-itself">Prepare for the exam itself</h3> <p>In my mind, English is always a language. We study it to communicate not to do exam. So I don’t want to or don’t have time to try hard for the exam. But you have to realize that, you enter a game, you must get the rules.</p> <p>So to grab the requirements and format of the exam, I learn from 2 main sources:</p> <ol> <li><a href="https://fastrackielts.com/">Fastrack IELTS</a>: An English course from a 8.5 teacher, even though I didn’t finish all the courses but I think it’s an actually good one.</li> <li><a href="https://www.fahasa.com/the-official-cambridge-guide-to-ielts-student-s-book-with-answers-with-dvd-rom.html">The Official Cambridge Guide to IELTS Student’s Book</a>: A book that everyone deserves!</li> </ol> <p>Beside, I recommend <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@Ieltsadvantage">IELTS Advantage</a> Youtube channel. They have a lot of useful tips and tricks.</p> <h3 id="speaking-preparation">Speaking Preparation</h3> <p>This is my most weakness skill. I only got 5.5 for Speaking :laughing:. So maybe my advice for this one won’t be so legit. I have a lot of pronunciation problems. Here are my resources:</p> <ol> <li><a href="https://elsaspeak.com/en/">Elsa Speak</a>: This app is already very popular. And its quality worth that.</li> <li>Playlist <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLD6B222E02447DC07">The Sound of English</a> by BBC.</li> </ol> <p>On another hand, you can join some foreign Discord servers to improve your real life English communication.</p> <h3 id="writing--reading-preparation">Writing &amp; Reading Preparation</h3> <p>To be honest I didn’t prepare much for 3 left skills, but I guess I can give some recommendations.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://writeandimprove.com/">Write &amp; Improve</a> from Cambridge: There are topic tasks for you to do, the website will score and give advice. But if you want to do IELTS tasks, you have do to some payments, I guess so.</li> <li><a href="https://www.fahasa.com/oxford-learner-s-pocket-phrasal-verbs-and-idioms.html">Oxford Learner’s Pocket Phrasal Verbs And Idioms</a> and related books: Offer a wide range of elegant words, but need to know how to use them with other tools to maximize the effiency.</li> <li><a href="https://learnenglish.britishcouncil.org/grammar">Grammar - British Council</a>: Too legit to introduce anything.</li> <li><a href="https://www.vocabulary.com/">Vocabulary</a>: a kinda advanced page about vocabulary.</li> </ul> <h3 id="listening-preparation">Listening Preparation</h3> <p>Maybe we only need to watch Youtube a lot for this skill? I will introduce some channels have short and meaningful videos.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@ProjectBetterSelf">Project Better Self</a>: self help and self improvement channel</li> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@crashcourse">Crash Course</a>: medium-length videos, have a lot of knowledge to entertain your brain</li> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@TEDEd">TedED</a>: I guess you already know this channel</li> </ul> <p>If you love listening, you can check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@CalNewportMedia">Cal Newport</a> in your free time. I love his books a lot. I don’t recommend TED because their topics recently focus on social sciences or politics, which I hate with a passion.</p> <h2 id="exam-day">Exam Day</h2> <p>I took the test on 26th Dec which is in my endterm exam period. So I feel really exhausted and don’t really motivated to do the exam. I register to take the exam at IDP Hai Ba Trung.</p> <p>In case of unwanted accidents, I go to the site pretty early. I took the Speaking exam in the morning and the rest in the afternoon.</p> <hr/> <p>I am done with my sharing, if you have any questions, don’t mind to ask!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Journal-of-Sciences"/><category term="languages"/><category term="english"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an honest review and my preparation for the exam]]></summary></entry></feed>